As part of unit testing, Python has several
assert methods one can use to help test the
functionality of a unit of code.
Unit testing, as we have seen, helps determine,
for a block of code, whether a tester is or
is not getting an anticipated result for that
block of code.
There are several different types of unit
tests, five of which are in this 534-assert
file.
Assert tests compare two values and return
either a true or false, depending upon the
comparison.
This code block is a continuation of the code
we used in the topic on unit tests.
We have the unittest library imported on line
1, and a class named TestMain that uses the
built-in TestCase function on line 3.
We previously ran this assertEqual test on
lines 5 through 8.
Thus, let's focus on some of these other assert
methods.
Lines 10 and 11 show an assertTrue test, a
test that asserts whether a statement is true.
On lines 13 through 16, we see an assertIs
test, which tests whether two variables use
the same memory space.
Lines 18 through 21 run an assertIn test to
see if one object is part of a list of objects.
Lines 23 through 25 test to see if a variable
is an instance of a class.
I have these lines commented out as classes
are beyond the scope of this exam, but assertIsInstance
is mentioned in the exam objectives, so I
wanted you to see an example of that type
of unit test.
How many of these tests do you expect to fail
in looking through these test conditions?
Let’s find out.
I will run this code, and one test failed,
the assertTrue test.
Why?
2 + 5 * 3 is not 21.
Remember, the order of operations dictates
that multiplication occurs before addition.
So, the answer to the math problem on line
11 is 17, not 21.
If we add parentheses around the addition
portion and test again, all tests will succeed.
In a real-life situation, you can use these
assertions to ensure a game flows the way
it should.
From a practical sense, you can have several
assert-type tests built and then use them
to plug in variables as needed to see if one’s
assertions about code are true and if not,
one can more easily isolate, diagnose, and
fix the problem, often a logic problem, with
the code.
We have reached the end of this section on
unit testing, so it is time for another code
analysis exercise.
Use the code you see here in this 534-analyze
file to answer the questions in the Review
5.3 exercise in your project workbook.
When you have answered those questions, come
back here and move to the next video, and
we will go over these answers.